"Fasting-Mimicking Diet Before
and After Chemotherapy"
Short-term food withdrawal during
chemotherapy may begin to solve
the long-standing problem
with most cancer treatments:
how to kill the tumor
without killing the patient?
Short-term fasting --
for example,
for 48 hours before chemo
and 24 hours afterwards --
may reduce side effects, reduce
chemotherapy-induced toxicity.
However, the potential tumor-
suppressing effects of fasting --
for example, its influence on tumor
growth, metastasis and prognosis --
have not been evaluated until now.
No, actually, sadly, they mean
"have not been evaluated until now,"
meaning they have not
been evaluated yet, period.
So in answering the question to fast
or not to fast before chemotherapy,
it should be emphasized
that the evidence provided
by human studies
is still very limited.
Some argue that reducing
the side effects alone
could improve efficacy,
since patients could
withstand higher doses.
For example, the heart and
kidney damage associated
with the widely prescribed
anti-cancer drugs limit
their full therapeutic potential.
It's not clear, though, that
maximizing the tolerated
chemo dose would achieve
longer survival or
better quality of life.
For now, I think we should
just be satisfied with
the fewer side effects for
fewer side effects' sake.
Some cancer docs urge caution,
concerned about malnutrition.
That concern is echoed
in official guidelines
on nutrition in cancer patients.
Because of the risks
of malnutrition and,
yeah, maybe a day
or two might not hurt,
but because patients might
be tempted to prolong fasting
episodes without firm evidence
of a benefit, they feel
fasting during chemotherapy
cannot be recommended.
Fasting proponents agree that
patients with severe weight loss,
muscle wasting or malnutrition --
probably not good candidates
for even short-term fasting.
But out of the hundreds of
patients that have been tracked,
there's no evidence of severe adverse
events in terms of malnutrition
or weight loss with short-term
fasting or fasting-mimicking diets.
And those patients who did
experience a weight loss
during fasting typically
recovered their weight
before the subsequent cycle
of chemo without detectable harm.
But look, even if there is a risk,
we're talking about cancer here.
Accepting trade-offs is kind
of the name of the game.
People are willing to put up
with the risk of severe,
even life-threatening side
effects all the time.
And even if it just helped
alleviate some of the side effects,
it might be worth a try.
Of course, meanwhile Big Pharma
is busy trying to come up with drugs
aimed at reproducing the
beneficial effects of fasting.
Although fasting mimicking drugs
may be preferred by patients
who would rather pop a pill
than go without eating,
it will be years before
they'll ever be on the market,
and it's hard to imagine drugs
will be developed that are
both as effective and
as safe as fasting.
So is there anything
we can tweak in our diet
to get similar benefits
without having to fast?
The way fasting works
is by reducing levels
of a cancer-promoting
growth hormone known as
insulin-like growth factor 1.
It's the reduced levels
of IGF-1 that mediate
the differential protection
of normal and cancer cells
in response to fasting
and improves chemo's
ability to kill cancer
but spare normal cells.
How do we know this?
Because restoration of IGF-1
was sufficient to reverse
the protective effect of fasting.
Check it out.
Here's the growth of two cancer cell
lines, breast cancer and melanoma,
in a petri dish after being
exposed to chemotherapy.
Survival rates dropped down
into the 60s or even 20s.
But the same dose in starved
cells works even better.
Same dose, same starvation,
but drip back a little IGF-1
and the starvation benefit vanishes.
So reducing IGF-1 signaling
may provide the dual benefits
by protecting normal cells while
reducing tumor progression
and may even help prevent
the cancer in the first place.
As I explained before in my
"How Not To Die from Cancer" video,
and an important video
about animal protein --
which kind of gives away
the punch line --
but fasting isn't the only way
to drop IGF-1 levels.
Yes, a few days of fasting
can cut levels in half,
but that's largely because
you're cutting your protein intake.
Protein is a key determinant of
circulating IGF-1 levels in humans,
suggesting that reduced
protein intake may become
an important component
of anticancer and anti-aging
dietary interventions, particularly
a reduction in animal protein.
If you compare those eating strictly
plant-based diets, getting about the
recommended daily intake of protein,
0.8 grams per kg of body weight,
and compare them to people just
as slender but eating more typical
American protein intake, going
on a calorie-restricted diet
may lower IGF-1 a little, but eating
a plant-based diet can lower it more.
So not only may a diet centered
around whole plant foods
down-regulate IGF-1 activity,
potentially slowing the aging process,
but may be a way of turning
anti-aging genes against cancer.